Inventory of the Wayne Fulton Gibbs Papers, 1925-1973
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Wayne Fulton Gibbs Papers, 1925-1973.
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Archives Acc. 1981.94
0.6 linear feet.
Papers of Wayne F. Gibbs, Professor of Accountancy at the College of William and Mary, include records of organizations for accounting and business students, 1920s-1950s; and accounts and audits for various student organizations in the 1930s.
Wayne Fulton Gibbs.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Biographical/Historical Information
Wayne Fulton Gibbs was born 23 April 1899 in Winchester, Illinois. He held the B.S. and M.S. degrees from the University of Illinois and was a certified public accountant. He first taught at Nebraska Wesleyan University, then at the College of William and Mary from 1926-1960. At the time of his retirement, he was chair of the Department of Business Administration as well as Professor of Accountancy.
Scope and Content Information
Wayne F. Gibbs acted as advisor and honorary member of student organizations related to accounting. The papers include the records of the Kappa Chapter of Beta Alpha Psi, the professional accounting fraternity, for 1929 to 1936; the records of the Omega Chapter of Alpha Kappa Psi, the professional commercial fraternity, for 1928 to 1935; and the records of the Accounting Club from 1938 to 1955. Gibbs also acted as auditor and financial advisor to various student organizations, and the papers include accounts and audit reports from the 1930s, particularly for The Flat Hat, Sigma Nu, Kappa Alpha Alumni Foundation, and the Cotillion Club. A few items in the papers pertain to the activities of his wife, Beatrice M. Gibbs.
Index Terms
College of William and Mary--History--20th century.; College of William and Mary. Accounting Club.; Alpha Kappa Psi. Omega Chapter.; Beta Alpha Psi. Kappa Chapter.; College student newspapers and periodicals--United States.
Contents List
- Beta Alpha Psi Records, 1930s., 5 folders (Box-folder 1:1-5)
  Beta Alpha Psi was established in 1919 as a professional accounting fraternity, for accounting students. The Kappa Chapter formed at the College of William and Mary in 1927.
  - Beta Alpha Psi, Kappa Chapter, Historical Records 1930-1933., 1 vol. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Brief history of the local chapter, established in 1927; creed and brief history of national organization; list of members; 1931 letter from President Chandler granting permission to hold bi-monthly meetings in Old Dominion Hall.
  - Beta Alpha Psi Minutes, March 1929-May 1930., 1 vol. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Minutes of meetings; attendance records and disbursements at end of volume.
  - Beta Alpha Psi Minutes, December 1930-May 1936., 1 vol. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Minutes of meetings; membership rolls at end of volume.
  - Beta Alpha Psi Correspondence, 1931-1935., 28 items (Box-folder 1:4)
    Correspondence concerning membership, annual banquet and competition papers, business with national organization; treasurer's reports; notes on economics.
  - Beta Alpha Psi, Alpha Chapter, Membership Roster 1973., 1 vol. (Box-folder 1:5)
    The Alpha Chapter is at the University of Illinois. Wayne Gibbs is listed as a member.
- Alpha Kappa Psi Minutes, February 1928-December 1935., 1 vol. (Box-folder 1:6)
  Alpha Kappa Psi was established in 1904 as a professional commercial fraternity, for business students. Its founders were students at New York University's evening School of Commerce, Accounts and Finance, which was newly created in 1900 to meet the double need for higher commercial education and for a college of accountancy. The Omega Chapter of Alpha Kappa Psi formed at the College of William and Mary in 1921, according to the records of the national organization.
  Minutes of Alpha Kappa Psi for February 1928 to December 1935, with attendance rolls at end of volume; letter from Douglas Dempsey to Mr. Quittmeyer, 16 October 1975, noting the discovery of the volume.
- Accounting Club Minutes, March 1938-May 1955., 1 folder (Box-folder 1:7)
  The Accounting Club was established in March 1938. It was renamed the Wayne F. Gibbs Accounting Club in 1961 to honor its faculty advisor.
  Minutes and attendance rolls, March 1938-May 1955.
- List of students in advanced accounting, 1926/27-1938/39, 2 pages. (Box-folder 1:8)
- Flat Hat Business Manager Record Books, 1932-1934., 2 vols. (Box-folder 2:1-2)
  The Flat Hat's Business Manager was a student, but Professor Gibbs acted as financial advisor and auditor to student publications. See Box 2, folder 3, for accounts in 1930 and for information on the business structure of student publications at William and Mary.
  Accounts of receipts and disbursements for the Flat Hat, for 1932/33 and 1933/34.
- Reports of audit and control performed by Wayne F. Gibbs, 1930-1934., 1 folder (Box-folder 2:3)
  Professor Gibbs acted as auditor and financial advisor to various student organizations, either on a regular basis or when financial problems arose.
  - Financial statements for student organizations, May 23, 1930., 4 pages.
    Financial statements for student organizations for the spring semester 1930: The Flat Hat, Women's Debate Council, J. Lesslie Hall Literary Society, YWCA, Men's Debate Council, YMCA, Phoenix Literary Society, Philomathian Literary Society. Includes detailed receipts and disbursements for The Flat Hat.
  - Correspondence re student publications, February 1934., 4 pages.
    In answer to an inquiry from the Financial Manager of Hampden-Sydney College regarding the supervision and structure of student publications at the College of William and Mary, Gibbs outlines the students' Board of Control, selection of the Editors-in-Chief and Business Managers and their staffs, and faculty supervision of the financial aspects.
  - Audits for Kappa Alpha Alumni Foundation, July 29, 1932., 14 pages.
    Audit of General Headquarters Committee of Kappa Alpha for 1927-1928, of Kappa Alpha Holding Corporation for 1923-1929, and of Kappa Alpha Alumni Foundation for 1923-1932, prepared for Dr. J. A. C. Chandler as president of the Kappa Alpha Alumni Foundation.
  - Accounts for Cotillion Club Dances, 1933-1934, 20 pages.
    Accounts for Cotillion Club Dances for February 1933, for June 1933, and for February 1934.
  - Account for German Club Dance, February 1934., 2 pages.
  - Audits of Sigma Nu, Epsilon Iota Chapter, February 1934-December 1934., 10 pages.
  - Accounts for William and Mary Athletic Association, June 1933-June 1934, 8 pages.
- William and Mary Business Studies: Study No. 1, 1955., 13 pages. (Box-folder 2:4)
  Attitudes of Graduates of the Business Department of the College of William and Mary Regarding Education and Preparation for the Business World. A somewhat inconclusive survey of graduates from ca. 1950 on the usefulness of various course offerings.
- Personal memorabilia of Wayne Gibbs., 11 items. (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Membership certificate of Wayne F. Gibbs in Alpha Kappa Psi, Omega Chapter, 27 May 1927
  - Membership certificate of Wayne F. Gibbs in Pi Gamma Mu, 17 August 1925.
  - E. H. Wells, Nebraska Wesleyan University, to Wayne F. Gibbs, 1 July 1926.
    Regrets Gibbs's leaving the university, appreciates his contributions to the Department of Economics and Sociology at Nebraska Wesleyan University.
  - Newspaper clippings concerning University of Illinois alumni., 1 page.
    Undated articles about alumni reunions and about Dudley Woodbridge, who received his law degree from U.I. and came to teach at the College of William and Mary.
  - The Ramp News, 25 December 1945.
    Newsletter from U.S. Navy ship LST 991 (re Gibbs's son?).
  - Greeting card.
    Mr. John Stewart Bryan sends greetings from The President's House, The College of William and Mary in Virginia. (With photograph of president's house.)
  - Program for President's Dinner to the Faculty, 21 November 1936.
  - Yearbooks, Williamsburg Branch A.A.U.W., 1933/34 and 1934/35., 2 items.
    Mrs. Wayne F. Gibbs was a member.
  - Sixty-Second Annual Convention, Virginia Branch, International Order of the King's Daughters and Sons, May 26-28, 1959., 2 items.
    Program; minutes by Beatrice M. Gibbs. The convention was held in Williamsburg.